Hello internet. I am RD Lady and in this
tutorial, I'm going to show you how to
extract models and textures from
PlayStation 2 games. This tutorial is a
bit long, so I split it in two videos.
In this video, I'm going to show how to
extract the textures from PlayStation 2
games and in the next video, I'm going
to show you how to extract the models
from PlayStation 2 games. Okay, but
before we start, I need to tell you
something very important about this
tutorial. Typically, I try to bring here
methods that can be used to extract
models and textures from most of games
that belong to a platform. But in the
specific case of PlayStation 2, the
model and texture extraction method is a
little bit complicated. The companies
that develop games for PlayStation 2,
they usually use their own file formats
and their own encryption methods. So, 3D
models and textures for games of
PlayStation 2 will have different
formats and different encryptions and
compressions depending on what company
worked on that game. So, this makes the
extraction process very complicated and
difficult. Each company, each game works
with a different file format. So, after
months of research, this is the only
method that I found that can overcome
this obstacle of many file formats by
using a PlayStation 2 emulator as
extraction source. Unfortunately, this
method is not very efficient. I have
tried so far six games and three or four
of them worked. I was able to extract
their models. So, it has about 50% of
chance of working. But, this was the
best generic method that I could find
for extracting textures and models from
PlayStation 2 games. So, now let's start
with the best method that we have. To
extract the textures, we're going to use
a tool named Texmod or
So, let's download and set up Texmod to
do the extraction of the textures.
Now that I downloaded Texmod, I'm going
to move it to the desktop area, so it's
going to be easier to work with it.
And Texmod comes compressed in a zip
format file, so we're going to just
extract it now. For extracting this
file, you can use WinRAR, WinZip, or any
other decompressor tool. So, Texmod
works like this. It will intercept the
textures that are rendered by a
PlayStation 2 emulator. So, now we have
to download the PlayStation 2 emulator
that will work together with Texmod. And
the PlayStation 2 emulator that we're
going to use is PCSX2,
but we're going to download a specific
version of this emulator, the version
0.9.8,
because this version is the only version
that's going to work later for us when
we're going to try to extract the 3D
models in the next video. So, let's
download the PCSX2.
And since I downloaded the portable
version, I just have to extract this
emulator to a folder, and after that I
have to download a BIOS that will work
together with the emulator.
There are many PlayStation 2 BIOS files
available online. You can find them in
any emulator websites.
So, after we downloaded the BIOS files,
we just have to extract them to a BIOS
folder that we can create inside the
emulator folder.
Now that we have downloaded both Texmod
and the PlayStation 2 emulator, now
let's open and set up Texmod to extract
the game textures.
So, the first thing we have to do to set
up Texmod is to click on the tab login
mode.
And here we have to select which program
will be monitored and intercepted by
Texmod to extract its textures. In our
case, we just have to select our
PlayStation 2 emulator.
As output format for the textures, I'm
selecting BMP, but you can select any
format.
And for the capture key or the log with
key, we have to select a key that is not
used as a shortcut key by the emulator.
In my case, I'm choosing the F11 key.
And the default output folder is an
output folder inside the Tex Mod folder.
So, I'm just going to leave this as
default. And when we extract the
textures, these textures will be saved
inside an output folder that is inside
Tex Mod folder.
After that, we just have to click in run
and the PlayStation 2 emulator will run
through the Tex Mod.
When we open the emulator for the first
time,
we just have to set some default
settings by clicking next.
And then we have to select one of those
BIOS that we have just downloaded. And
then we just click in finish.
And once we open the emulator, we're
going to select which game we want to
emulate. Here, I'm going to use Resident
Evil 4 as an example. I'm not going to
show you how to download Resident Evil
4, but you can download that from any
torrent website.
And I'm just going to show here my video
plugin configuration. I'm using the
GDSX9
plugin with these settings here, but
these settings should be the default
ones, so you should not worry about
that.
So, let's run the game and let's skip to
a part where are the textures that we
want to extract.
So, Texmod works like this. Every time a
given texture is selected for
extraction, it will be showing in green.
So, an object that has a selected
texture will be green. This is how
Texmod show us which is the texture that
is selected for extraction. So, we can
use the minus and plus keys to browse
through the textures, minus to go back
and plus to go forward until we see the
texture that we want to extract
selected, which means we keep pressing
plus or minus until we see the texture
that we want in green. When the texture
that we want to extract is green, then
we finally can press F11 or the shortcut
key to save the texture. So, this is how
it works. And I'll keep doing this cycle
of going through the textures, pressing
plus or minus until I find my texture
that I want in green, and then I'll
press F11 to save it. I will repeat this
until I have all the textures that I
want. And all the textures that I want
will be saved in the output folder
inside Texmod folder.
Now that I extracted all the textures
that I want, we can see here that the
textures don't look good. It seems that
the alpha channels got inverted somehow.
Leon's hair, for example, should be
brown, but it's kind of bluish. So, it
seems that the red and blue colors got
inverted. All the textures are going to
look wrong like that when you extract
them using TexMod. So, I'm going to show
you a method to fix it. And we're going
to fix it using So, let's download
and run
So, here in let's open the texture
that we want to fix.
After opening the texture that we want
to fix, we're going to go here in the
color menu
and then in components
and then we're going to click in channel
mixer.
Here in the color mixer tool, we're
going to first select the output channel
of the color red.
And then we're going to set the red
color as zero.
And the blue color as 100.
And now we're going to do exactly the
opposite to the output channel blue.
We're going to select the blue output
channel.
And then we're going to set the red
color to 100 and the blue color to zero.
So by performing these steps, we were
able to invert the color channels and
our texture finally looks correct.
And now that we fixed this texture,
we're going to export it to any image
format that we want.
In my case here, I'm going to export it
as TGA, but you can select any other
format.
And now that you learn how to fix the
textures, you just have to repeat this
process to all the textures that you
have extracted using TexMod.
And this is how you extract textures
from PlayStation 2 games. In the next
video, I'm going to show you how to
extract the models from PlayStation 2
games.
As I mentioned it before, this is the
best generic method that I could find
that could work for a large number of
games. This method is efficient when
compared to other methods that depends
on a specific scripts that require
programming skills for example, but this
method is far away from being perfect
and it doesn't work for all the games.
But unfortunately, this was best method
that I could find after a long time of
research. Please don't forget to give a
like if you like this video and
subscribe to this channel to receive
more tutorials. So, I see you in the
next part of this tutorial where I'm
going to show you how to extract the
models from PlayStation 2 games. See you
next time.